Loudoun County Extension Homemakers Club Records 1926-1994
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Loudoun County Extension Homemaker's Club Records
Thomas Balch Library
M 0127
2.5 cubic ft..
This collection contains the records of the Loudoun County Extension Homemakers Club. It includes minutes, newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, photographs, newsletters, correspondence, agendas, event pamphlets, recipes, attendance, speeches, information on club activities, as well as information on the history of the club.
Carolyn Grubb, Purcellville VA and Dorothy Martel, Middleburg, VA
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Carolyn Grubb, Purcellville VA and Dorothy Martel, Middleburg, VA
Alternative Form Available
None
Accruals
2001.0005, 2009.0245
Historical Information
The Loudoun County Extension Homemakers Club developed as an arm of the United States Department of Agriculture Extension Services [USDA]. Funded and overseen by a partnership of federal, state, and local governments, Extension Services were first established as a nationwide system in 1914 by the Smith-Lever Act. The Extension Services were designed to aid farmers by providing educational classes in homemaking to white farm women. The program quickly took off and by 1915, 335 home economics schools were held for 21,000 farm women all over the country. In 1936, a group of Extension homemakers met with the USDA in order to form the National Extension Homemakers Council to further promote educational efforts. Extension Homemakers clubs were segregated, leading many black communities to form their own clubs, such as the Housekeeper's Club formed in Aldie, Virgina in 1914.
Loudoun County home demonstrations were first organized by Grace Heyl (1901-1991), the county's Home Demonstration Agent, in 1923. By 1926, ten Extension Homemakers clubs were established in the county. In that same year, representatives of the existing Extension Clubs, a county agent, and a district representative all came together in order to create a Loudoun County Extension Homemakers Council. The council was composed of ten members and grew as the number of clubs in the county grew. By 1975 there were fifteen clubs and approximately 300 homemakers.
The Homemakers Club served as a place where women came together to learn sewing, quilting, cooking, housekeeping techniques, and various other homemaking skills; later the Club evolved. It became a source of discussion of gender roles, volunteer work, and of leadership among women. In 1994, every Loudoun County Extension Homemaker Club member was invited to attend a meeting to discuss the future of the club and voted to disband.
Scope and Content
This collection contains the records of the Loudoun County Extension Homemakers Club. It includes minutes, newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, photographs, newsletters, correspondence, agendas, event pamphlets, recipes, attendance, speeches, information on club activities, as well as information on the history of the club.
The earliest records of the club's activities are in the form of minutes beginning in 1926 and ending in 1947. The minutes preserved by the Club are photocopies; the whereabouts of the original minutes are unknown. Minutes are arranged which each new year beginning in December and concluding in November. After 1985, only scattered minutes are available. Scrapbooks dating between 1961 and 1994 are included in this collection, and include photographs and ephemera as well as "Achievement Day" materials and yearbooks. "Achievement Day" was an annual event where club members celebrated their accomplishments and activities from the previous year. Loose items were removed from each scrapbook and foldered for better preservation of the materials.
A few abbreviations are used over the course of this collection. Loudoun County is abbreviated to "LoCo" and Extension Homemakers is has been abbreviated to "E.H." This is an open collection and additional material may be received.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
"African American History, Housekeeper's Club," Vertical File, Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Ancestry.com. Virginia, Birth Records, 1912-2014, Delayed Birth Records, 1854-1911 [database on-line]. Provo, UT, USA: Ancestry.com Operations, Inc., 2015.
Loudoun County Extension Homemakers Club Records, (M 0127), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Oregon State Library; Oregon Death Index 1931-1941; Reel Title: State of Oregon Death Index; Year Range: 1991-2000
Other Finding Aid
PastPerfect
Technical Requirements
None
Related Material
Loudoun County Fair Association 4-H Collection (VC 0017), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA, Home Interest Club Records, 1903-2013 (M 077), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA. A History of the Housekeeper's Club, Vertical File, Thomas Balch Library
Contents List
  - 1
    - Loudoun County Extension Homemaker's Club History 1976-1977, 1985, 1987, 1992, 1994
    - Minutes 1926-1947
    - Minutes 1948-1949
    - Minutes 1949-1950
    - Minutes 1950-1951
    - Minutes 1951-1952
    - Minutes 1952-1953
    - Minutes 1953-1955
    - Minutes 1955-1959
    - Minutes 1959-1962
    - Minutes 1962-1963
    - Minutes 1964-1965
    - Minutes 1965-1969
    - Minutes 1970-1974
  - 2
    - Minutes 1975-1978
    - Minutes 1978-1981
    - Minutes 1982-1985
    - Minutes and other materials, 1992
    - Loudoun County Extension Homemakers Public Relations Report 1987
    - Loudoun County Extension Homemakers Club's Newsletter: Focus 1978- 1981
    - Loudoun County Extension Homemakers Club's Newsletter: Focus 1982-1989
    - Loudoun County Extension Homemakers Newsletter: Focus 1983- 1984, 1989-1993
    - Copy of Loudoun County Extension Homemakers "Watson Club" 1961, 1976-1977
    - Items Removed from Scrapbook Loudoun County Extension Homemakers "Watson Club" 1961, 1976-1977
    - Copy of Loudoun Extension Homemakers Scrapbook 1976-1980
    - Items Removed from Scrapbook: Loudoun County Extension Homemakers 1976-1980
    - Items Removed from Scrapbook: Loudoun County Extension Homemakers Scrapbook 1978, 1988-1994
  - 3
    - Loudoun County Extension Homemakers 1974-1978
    - Watson 1976-1978
    - Loudoun Extension Homemakers Scrapbook 1976-1980
    - Watson Scrapbook 1979-1982, 1987
    - Loudoun Extension Homemakers Scrapbook 1980-1987
    - Loudoun County Extension Homemakers Scrapbook 1988- 1994
  - 4
    - Photographs Removed from: Loudoun County Extension Homemakers Club History 1976-1977, 1985, 1987, 1992, 1994 (vc_0088_0001)
    - Photographs Removed from: Loudoun County Extension Homemakers Public Relations Report 1987 (vc_0088_0002-vc_ 0011_0007)
    - Photographs Removed from Scrapbook: Loudoun County Extension Homemakers "Watson Club" 1961, 1976-1977 1 of 2 (vc_0088_0008-vc_0088_0016)
    - Photographs Removed from Scrapbook: Loudoun County Extension Homemakers "Watson Club" 1961, 1976-1977 2 of 2 (vc_0088_17-vc_0088_0023)
    - Photographs Removed from Scrapbook: Loudoun County Extension Homemakers 1976-1980 1 of 2 (vc_0088_0024-vc_0088_0025)
    - Photographs Removed from Scrapbook: Loudoun County Extension Homemakers 1976-1980 2 of 2 (vc_0088_0026-vc_0088_0029)
  - 5
    - Loudoun County Home Demonstration Club's Gavel, 1971
    - National Extension Homemakers Council President's Pin